<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>infectiology on medist.org</title><link>https://medist.org/tags/infectiology/</link><description>Recent content in infectiology on medist.org</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medist.org/tags/infectiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pneumonia</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/pneumonia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/pneumonia/</guid><description>Classification community-acquired pneumonia (CAP), acquired outside of hospital nosocomial pneumonia, acquired in hospital, further subdivided into hospital-acquired pneumonia (HAP), acquired &amp;gt;= 48 hours after admission ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP), acquired &amp;gt;= 48 hours after intubation Therapeutic decisions are futher guided by immunocompetence, with immunocompromised patients having different potential pathogens, including fungal infections, parasites and uncommon viral/bacterial species.
Diagnosis history with fever, cough, dyspnea and sputum production vital signs including blood pressure, breathing rate, SpO2, mental state (GCS) calculate qSOFA score laboratory findings leukocytosis, early sign elevated CRP, can lag behind leukocytes elevated PCT is highly specific for bacterial infections urea is needed for CURB-65 score arterial blood gases for respiratory insufficiency auscultation imaging chest X-ray can often identify consolidations/infiltrates/cavitations CT can provide further clarification in inconclusive or negative radiographs ultrasound can identify pleural effusions Microbiologic testing blood cultures sputum cultures/stain urinary testing for S.</description></item><item><title>Sepsis</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/sepsis/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/sepsis/</guid><description>qSOFA high score = high risk
GCS &amp;lt; 15 breathing frequency &amp;gt;= 22/min systolic bp &amp;lt;= 100 mmHg Early management i.v. volume and circulatory support, MAP &amp;gt;= 65 mmHg get samples start empiric antibiotics first doses is a normal dose, even in renal failure aim for application within max. 30 minutes! central venous catheter, arterial cathether treat the focus (change lines/catheter, surgery, etc&amp;hellip;) Volume management Isotonic crystalloids: 30 ml/kg KG in hypotension and lactate &amp;gt;= 4 mmol/l careful administration in heart failure Circulatory support Noradrenaline: first choice, the maximum rate of 1.</description></item><item><title>Fever checklist</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/fever/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/fever/</guid><description>Temperature &amp;gt;= 38.3 °C (100.9 °F), in immunocompromised/neutropenia &amp;gt;= 38.0 ° (100.4 °F)
Diagnostic History: signs of infection, post-surgery, drug induced fever CRP, Leukocytes, ggf. Procalcitonin blood count, if needed differential blood count fever in neutropenia: absolute neutrophile count &amp;lt; 500 to 1.000/µl (= neutrophils (%) * leucocytes count) Blood cultures (two pairs from to sites) Urine sample, sputum samples, swabs Ultrasound, X-Ray if CT is planned Therapy Paracetamol Antibiotics depending on focus</description></item></channel></rss>