<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>general on medist.org</title><link>https://medist.org/tags/general/</link><description>Recent content in general on medist.org</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medist.org/tags/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Protective lung ventilation</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/protective_lung_ventilation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/protective_lung_ventilation/</guid><description>General Protective lung ventilation aims for low tidal volume ventilation. A large study has shown a markedly dekrease in mortality, when patients with acute lung injury/ards were ventilatied with low tidal volumes. Today, the protective lung ventilation algorithm by the ards network provides a resonable default approach for mechanically ventilated patiens, especially those at risk for devloping ARDS
Ventilation setup and adjustment Calculate the predicted body weight (men: 50 + 0.</description></item><item><title>Pneumonia</title><link>https://medist.org/calculators/pneumonia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/calculators/pneumonia/</guid><description>Pneumonia Severity Index (PSI) Calculates the PSI-Score based on this article. The PSI-Score can be used to stratify the mortality in community acquired pneumonia.
Reset Demographic factors age Sex male female Nursing home resident Coexisting illness Neoplastic disease Liver disease Congestive heart failure Cerebrovascular disease Renal disease Physical-examination findings Altered mental status Respiratory rate &amp;ge; 30/min Systolic blood pressure &amp;lt; 90 mmHg Temperature &amp;lt; 35&amp;deg;C or &amp;ge; 40&amp;deg;C Pulse &amp;ge; 125/min Laboratory and radiographic findings Arterial pH &amp;lt; 7.</description></item><item><title>Pneumonia</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/pneumonia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/pneumonia/</guid><description>Classification community-acquired pneumonia (CAP), acquired outside of hospital nosocomial pneumonia, acquired in hospital, further subdivided into hospital-acquired pneumonia (HAP), acquired &amp;gt;= 48 hours after admission ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP), acquired &amp;gt;= 48 hours after intubation Therapeutic decisions are futher guided by immunocompetence, with immunocompromised patients having different potential pathogens, including fungal infections, parasites and uncommon viral/bacterial species.
Diagnosis history with fever, cough, dyspnea and sputum production vital signs including blood pressure, breathing rate, SpO2, mental state (GCS) calculate qSOFA score laboratory findings leukocytosis, early sign elevated CRP, can lag behind leukocytes elevated PCT is highly specific for bacterial infections urea is needed for CURB-65 score arterial blood gases for respiratory insufficiency auscultation imaging chest X-ray can often identify consolidations/infiltrates/cavitations CT can provide further clarification in inconclusive or negative radiographs ultrasound can identify pleural effusions Microbiologic testing blood cultures sputum cultures/stain urinary testing for S.</description></item><item><title>Acute Kidney Injury</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/acute_kidney_injury/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/acute_kidney_injury/</guid><description>AKI = acute kidney injury is classified further intp prerenal, renal, postrenal
Diagnostic criteria RIFLE AKIN doesn&amp;rsquo;t account for non-oliguric states Diagnostic approach Ultrasound postrenal obstruction prerenal: low volume Blood Na, K (and pH can easily be tested with ABG) Creatinine, BUN/Urea Cystatin C specific antibodies in autoimmune AKI &amp;hellip; Urine Urinalysis Osmolarity Na/Urea, Creatinine low Na indicates prerenal cause Used to calculate fractional excretion of sodium or urea fractional excretion of sodium &amp;lt; 1 %: prerenal, &amp;gt; 2 % renal, cannot be used with diuretics fractional excretion of urea &amp;lt; 35 % prernal, &amp;gt; 50 % renal, not influenced by diuretics Therapy improve renal perfusion stop nephrotoxic medications NSAIDs, aminoglykosides, ACE-inhibitors, AT-receptor blockers, etc.</description></item><item><title>ABG Calculators</title><link>https://medist.org/calculators/abg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/calculators/abg/</guid><description>Expected secondary responses Calculates the expected secondary responses in paCO2 and HCO3- based on this paper
paCO2 Reference: 36 - 44 HCO3- Reference: 22 - 26 Primary change Secondary reaction Metabolic acidosis Expected paCO2 of {{ metAcidosisResultingPCO2 }} mmHg
40 − [(24 − HCO3-) × 1.2] Metabolic alkalosis Expected paCO2 of {{ metAlkalosisResultingPCO2 }} mmHg
40 + [(HCO3- − 24) × 0.7] Acute respiratory acidosis Expected HCO3- of {{ acRespAcidosisResultingHCO3 }} mmHg</description></item><item><title>Sepsis</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/sepsis/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/sepsis/</guid><description>qSOFA high score = high risk
GCS &amp;lt; 15 breathing frequency &amp;gt;= 22/min systolic bp &amp;lt;= 100 mmHg Early management i.v. volume and circulatory support, MAP &amp;gt;= 65 mmHg get samples start empiric antibiotics first doses is a normal dose, even in renal failure aim for application within max. 30 minutes! central venous catheter, arterial cathether treat the focus (change lines/catheter, surgery, etc&amp;hellip;) Volume management Isotonic crystalloids: 30 ml/kg KG in hypotension and lactate &amp;gt;= 4 mmol/l careful administration in heart failure Circulatory support Noradrenaline: first choice, the maximum rate of 1.</description></item><item><title>Nutrition Calculators</title><link>https://medist.org/calculators/nutrition/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/calculators/nutrition/</guid><description>Ideal weight Calculate the ideal weight, based on the formula 48,4 + 77 * (height - 150 cm) (German Society for Nutrition). The conversion to lb uses the factor 1 kg = 2.2 lb.
height (cm) weight (kg) weight (lb) Calculates the ideal weight, based on the Devine formula 50 kg (female 45.5 kg) + 0.9 kg * (height - 152 cm). The conversion to lb uses the factor 1 kg = 2.</description></item><item><title>Nutrition</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/nutrition/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/nutrition/</guid><description>Phases of ciritcal illness early acute, day 1-2: catabolism late acute, day 4-7: lower catabolism reconvalescence, &amp;gt; day 7: increase of anabolism or chronic: persisting catabolism General establish current status (NUTRIC Score, MUST Score, etc.) caloric need/day (acute phase) BMI &amp;lt; 30: 24 kcal/kg weight (= current weight) BMI 30-50: 11-14 kcal/kg weight (= current weight minus hyperhydration) BMI &amp;gt; 50: 22-25 kcal/kg weight (= ideal weight) caloric need (reconvalescence) BMI &amp;lt; 30: 36 kcal/kg BMI &amp;gt; 30: inidivdual goal, consult nutritionist caloric need (special cases) sever burns: 40 kcal/kg liver failure: 35-40 kcal/kg malnutrition: 25-30 kcal/kg Acute phase (Parenteral) start with 75 % of calculated caloric need check glucose regularly high glucose: reduce caloric intake to 25 to 50% normal glucose: increase caloric intake to 100 % check triglycerides twice per week, high tg increase risk of pancreatitis check phosphate in severe malnutrition or in alcoholism normal phosphate: increase intake to 100 % low phostphate: lower intake to 25 %, substitue phosphate aim for 100 % intake on day 7 Enteral Nutrition aim for enteral nutrition to reduce risk for catheter associated infections if nasogastric/orogastric tube is not feasible, consider PEG Contraindications: disruptions of enteral motility (ileus, etc.</description></item><item><title>Fever checklist</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/fever/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/fever/</guid><description>Temperature &amp;gt;= 38.3 °C (100.9 °F), in immunocompromised/neutropenia &amp;gt;= 38.0 ° (100.4 °F)
Patient history respiratory: coughing, dyspnea, pleuritic pain gastrointestinal: vomiting, diarrhea, abdominal pain with location post-surgery: time of surgey, protheses, etc. urinary: dysuria, polyuria previous medications (think drug induced fever) previous antibiotics can influence future therapy previous infections (multiresistant bacteria) rheumatic diseases Diagnostic CRP, Leukocytes, ggf. Procalcitonin blood count, if needed differential blood count fever in neutropenia: absolute neutrophile count &amp;lt; 500 to 1.</description></item><item><title>NIV Checklist</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/niv/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/niv/</guid><description>Contraindications Missing spontaneous breathing Gasping Obstructed airway Gastrointestinal bleeding Ileus non-hypercapnic coma Relative contraindications Hypercapnic coma Agitation Interface incompatibility/not tolerated by patient/anatomical difficulties Severe hypoxemia Severe acidosis (pH &amp;lt; 7,1) Success criteria Dyspnea reduced Conciousness improved Breathing frequency reduced pCO2 reduced pH normalizing arterial SaO2 &amp;gt; 85% Heart frequency normalizing Settings initial PEEP 5 - 8 mbar Below 5: re-check indication Increase up to 10 mbar, depending on need Pinsp below 20 - 25 mbar driving pressure &amp;lt; 15 mbar Tidal volume 6 - 8 ml/kg Rule of thumb: 400 - 500 ml Dyspnoea might cause initial high volumes backup frequency 10 - 15 fIO: aim for SpO2 &amp;gt;= 90 %, usually fIO 30-35 % I:E 1:2 to 1:25</description></item></channel></rss>