<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ventilation on medist.org</title><link>https://medist.org/tags/ventilation/</link><description>Recent content in ventilation on medist.org</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medist.org/tags/ventilation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Protective lung ventilation</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/protective_lung_ventilation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/protective_lung_ventilation/</guid><description>General Protective lung ventilation aims for low tidal volume ventilation. A large study has shown a markedly dekrease in mortality, when patients with acute lung injury/ards were ventilatied with low tidal volumes. Today, the protective lung ventilation algorithm by the ards network provides a resonable default approach for mechanically ventilated patiens, especially those at risk for devloping ARDS
Ventilation setup and adjustment Calculate the predicted body weight (men: 50 + 0.</description></item><item><title>NIV Checklist</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/niv/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/niv/</guid><description>Contraindications Missing spontaneous breathing Gasping Obstructed airway Gastrointestinal bleeding Ileus non-hypercapnic coma Relative contraindications Hypercapnic coma Agitation Interface incompatibility/not tolerated by patient/anatomical difficulties Severe hypoxemia Severe acidosis (pH &amp;lt; 7,1) Success criteria Dyspnea reduced Conciousness improved Breathing frequency reduced pCO2 reduced pH normalizing arterial SaO2 &amp;gt; 85% Heart frequency normalizing Settings initial PEEP 5 - 8 mbar Below 5: re-check indication Increase up to 10 mbar, depending on need Pinsp below 20 - 25 mbar driving pressure &amp;lt; 15 mbar Tidal volume 6 - 8 ml/kg Rule of thumb: 400 - 500 ml Dyspnoea might cause initial high volumes backup frequency 10 - 15 fIO: aim for SpO2 &amp;gt;= 90 %, usually fIO 30-35 % I:E 1:2 to 1:25</description></item></channel></rss>