<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>endocrinology on medist.org</title><link>https://medist.org/tags/endocrinology/</link><description>Recent content in endocrinology on medist.org</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medist.org/tags/endocrinology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hyponatremia</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/hyponatremia/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/hyponatremia/</guid><description>Introduction Alterations of sodium reflect disturbances of the body water. Hyponatremia occurs in 15 to 20 % of hospitalized patients. This condition poses a challenge for diagnosis and treatment. The terminology and definitions of hyponatremia are often inconsistent and confusing. This checklist is based on a European guideline from 2014, with some additional context from UpToDate.
Measuring sodium You measure sodium via photometric or ion selective electrodes. Photometric measurements can be affected by the osmolality.</description></item><item><title>Adrenal Crisis</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/adrenal_crisis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/adrenal_crisis/</guid><description>Adrenal crisis describes an acute adrenal insufficiency, often presenting as hypotension refractory to fluids and vasopressors.
Causes chronic adrenal insufficiency most often in patients with primary adrenal insufficiency, can also occur in secondary and tertiary insufficiency triggers: increased demand for glucocorticoids (infection, surgery, trauma, &amp;hellip;) abrupt withdrawal of exogenous glucocorticoids acute adrenal insufficiency pituitary infarction acute adrenal gland destruction (hemorrhage, trauma) Presentation volume depletion and hypotension, often refractory to fluids and vasopressors</description></item><item><title>Diabetic Ketoacidosis</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/dka/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/dka/</guid><description>Diabetic ketoacidosis is a severe and potential life-threatening complication of diabetic mellitus. Glucose levels are usually moderately elevated, however they can range from normal/slightly increased levels (euglycemic states) to high levels exceeding 900 mg/dl in comatose patients. The treatment relies on fluid &amp;amp; electrolyte replacement, insulin administration and glucose administration.
Guidelines of from different regions have variations in therapy, for instance the ADA suggests half-isotonic (0.45 %) saline in the fluid replacement regime, the Joint British Diabetes Society and the German guideline recommend 0.</description></item><item><title>Hyperkalemia</title><link>https://medist.org/checklists/hyperkalemia/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://medist.org/checklists/hyperkalemia/</guid><description>Hyperkalemia is a common clinical problem, caused by the inability to excrete potassium due to renal impairment or drugs. The therapy is ultimately to increase potassium excretion, either via medications or by dialysis. The first cause of action however, is to shift the potassium into the cells.
General measure twice, high Potassium can be caused by hemolytic blood or prolonged tourniquet use/muscular activity when drawing blood large IV access you might need a dialysis catheter in the future consider increased DOAC-levels in renal failure, in case you want to insert a central catheter monitoring ECG and NIBP medication history Potassium-sparing diuretics (spironolactone, eplerenone, amiloride, triamterene) several other medications might need adjustment based on current renal function Stratification Different strategies exist to assess the severity of hyperkalemia, using combinations of potassium levels, cardiac abnormalities and comorbidities.</description></item></channel></rss>